welcome to cultivating wisdom with john
vraviki
we are live streaming every saturday
morning at 10 a.m eastern time
the discord server and the links for the
discord server will be in the
description of this video
is continuing to have the daily
meditation sets
we want to put together a compilation
video to mark the end of the daily
sits it would be helpful if everyone
could please send in a clip of no more
than 10 seconds
about your experience as part of the
sega community
to amarr at john vervicky.com
amar john vervicky.com for those of you
who are joining for
the meditation practice please
take a look at the description of this
video and you'll find links uh to
previous meditation and contemplation
uh lessons and sits uh please do the
first lesson and continue to do a lesson
or maybe two lessons every week
continue to meet with us saturday
morning and
you'll very quickly integrate into
the entire ecology practices and into
the sangha and the discord community
i would ask everybody to please like
this stream to increase the
visibility on the youtube algorithm we
go for an
hour now we go from 10 a.m to 11 a.m
eastern time at the end there'll be a
time for questions please limit
questions
to this ecology of practices
but if you have more general questions
please join me
uh the third friday of every month at 3
p.m eastern time
live streamed on youtube so we are
always will begin
a saturday dharma day or we're thinking
of calling it saturday sanga day
a little bit more alliteration eh um so
we're going to begin always with sitting
we'll begin as normally with
chanting if you're unfamiliar with the
chanting don't worry about it you'll
find it in the lessons as you work your
way through
just do as best you can we'll begin with
chanting then we'll go into a silent set
uh we'll cut to the second camera i'll
go to the white board and we'll begin
the dharma and we'll begin
the second stage we'll move into the
high school in
uh the wisdom of my patient course and
we'll talk start talking about stoicism
but first let's get ourselves oriented
not get ourselves into our basic posture
set your phones on do not disturb
we will begin when i together when i say
begin
[Music]
one
on
[Music]
one
begin your silence set
slowly come out of your practice trying
as best you can to integrate what you
cultivated in your practice
with your everyday consciousness
cognition character and communitas
perhaps by reciting the five promises
okay i'm going to move to the whiteboard
and we will begin the dharma
so we're going to begin with
a background today for an understanding
of stoicism
you should be reading through the second
degree in the mclaren book the wisdom of
lipatia
but let's begin and as always
we begin with the exemplary figure of
socrates
and we went uh through the channel to
epicurus this time we're going through
another one of his disciples we of
course will end with his greatest
disciple
which is who is plato but here's another
very important one
and this is antisthenes
he was a follower of socrates
and unlike he wrote stuff but he didn't
put as much
emphasis on theory and argumentation as
plato did
and so people asked him well what did
you
what did you learn from socrates and he
said something
that is either extremely trivial
or extremely profound depending on your
reaction to it
and what did he say he what he said is i
learned how to converse
with myself
and of course this is the logos dialogue
all right now
one of the things we may say is big deal
i talk to myself all day long
and i take it and most people who
followed
and destinies took it that he didn't
mean that
he meant something that is a radical
transformation
of how we talk to ourselves all day long
but let's ask a question um that isn't
really asked here
at least directly but is asked directly
very much in modern cognitive sciences
something
and even in modern uh psychotherapy why
do we talk to each other
sorry not to each other why do we talk
to ourselves
all day long and you could see that i
was
leaping ahead a little bit of my
thinking it has to do with the fact
that we of course learn to talk
by talking to other people and in fact
here's an interesting thing that is
becoming more and more the case
in in the sense that we're realizing it
more and more to be true
the brain's relationship to itself your
brain's relationship to
itself is a mesh overlaps with is often
not distinguished from
your brain's relationship to other
brains so
one way of thinking about this is
cognition
you're thinking and you're making sense
of things
is not primarily monological
it's not a monologue it is
primarily dialogical
that in order to think we think best
when we think
dialogically
and there's more and more evidence that
we are actually better
when we're doing that in actual dialogue
and we'll talk about this when we
talk about the neoplatonic practice of
dialectic
which is using this relationship of how
we talk to each other
and how we talk to ourselves in order to
gauge
in significant transformation
so let's let's remember this
cognition is inherently dialogical even
though our culture
pretends and it is a very significant
form of bullshitting pretense
that we are monological beings uh that
that's how our thinking primarily
operates and works um we carry around
other people
in our heads all day long and some of
you might have
encountered that aspect a little bit
more saliently
in some of the practices uh we do with
meditative inquiry um and meta and
things like that
uh the five factors inquiring
mindfulness etc okay so
this idea that we're inherently
dialogical and of course
socrates models that
um so plato writes dialogues in which
socrates
is in discussion and sock and will come
back to this point
socrates makes a continual argument he
makes it repeatedly
that his dialoguing with other people
and his process of self-examination are
one
nor they're not one in the same but
they're completely out one with each
other
they're mutually independent trading
mutually uh
affording of each other all right so
let's pick this up
so the idea here is we're doing this
all day long our thinking is inherently
biological
now what that means i want to say
something here that's
and it's intended to be a little bit
provocative i'm tutored
right untutored inner dialogue
is better than
no no dialogue at all
okay that means
we do it because it's adaptive um it
really uh
helps our cognition uh when you meet
unfortunate individuals that haven't had
that proper
engagement uh with dialogue and socially
distributed cognition
uh they are seriously truncated uh as
uh cognitive agents it's questionable
um not in a moral sense but in a
metaphysical sense whether they are
persons
uh so this is why we do it we do it
because we have internalized
we'll come back to that remember when we
talked about internalizing this age we
have internalized the capacity
uh to generate thought through speech
by speaking with others and then
listening to others and then we can do
that
uh with ourselves so this is better than
no dialogue at all
but and this is a very important but
you know this is a stoic principle evil
doesn't come from when we choose what is
bad
evil comes when we choose a lesser good
in place of a greater good
untutored dialogue is better than no
dialogue at all
it's adaptive but that doesn't mean it's
optimal or the best for
us because
most of this inner dialogue is narrative
in nature
and we practice narrative and this is
daniel hudo's idea we're constantly
practicing narrative
we constantly teaching our kids
narrative when we simplify narrative
because it's actually not
natural to us we have to practice it we
use dialogue to get good at narrative
and then we internalize it
and we start to see ourselves and
identify with ourselves as a story
we're a story and there's a story going
on here right and this is narrative
also very adaptive narrative allows you
to identify with your future self
and your past it creates a temporally
extended itself
which is great for planning it's great
for long-term moral responsibility you
can hold me responsible
for something that i did 10 years ago
because there is a narrative identity
between me now
and that person then again narrative is
adaptive it's needed
right but the problem with narrative
right is
it creates a narrative bias
see people are hungry for narrative and
like anything that's adaptive and we
hunger for
it can be hijacked in an addictive
fashion so what i mean by people are
hungry for narrative
well there's some horrible event on the
news and what do people need
they need to know yeah what's the story
what's the story what's the story
and then once they get the story there's
like oh okay it's like
the the the consequences of what that
world will event haven't disappeared
but now there's a story and what what we
we see
is that what narrative tends to do is it
tends to create a
whole bunch of biases along with it
narrative drives the narrative bias
uh i hope that this blue is still
fizzled is this still okay the blue
that's still good okay it drives
confirmation bias
so the confirmation bias is and we're
going to need this when we talk about
um active open-mindedness confirmation
bias is our tendency to only look for
evidence that confirms
what we believe right so
when people get a story they will tend
to
only notice and find relevant and
salient things that fit their story
and they will tend to ignore any of the
evidence that could potentially
challenge it
so an obvious case where the narrative
bias is driving the confirmation bias is
conspiracy theory thinking
where people think they have some story
that makes sense of everything
and then they engage in the confirmation
bias
the other thing that that this drives is
it drives
over estimation biases
and these interact with each other by
the way these two biases
the overestimation bias is people think
when they have a story
they have all of the information about a
particular situation
and they also overestimate how how
good they are at making sense of things
so all of these biases kick in again
this is right these they are precisely
powerful biases because they are
hijacking something that is
adaptive in nature
but maybe we can do better
the other problem with the another way
in which the inner dialogue
often goes off the rails is rumination
you know what this is like when you get
in in an anxiety spiral
and you get all these biases also
spinning on each other and you keep
thinking in a way that's driving your
anxiety you can't let it go
or your depression and you start to spin
in rumination
this is a very powerful driver of
anxiety and depression
and it's a very complicated process but
it is very much driven by the fact
that your cognition is inherently
dialogical in nature so
i'm tutored it's adaptive one more time
it's it's adaptive that's why we do it
but it's so compelling and addictive
also because it's so adaptive and like
anything
that is adaptive it can become
maladaptive
so the stoics are right the cynics and
the followers of
socrates were looking at this and
especially antisthenes and his followers
and they were saying all right the
problem so what anticipates is basically
saying
when i learned how to converse with
myself is
untutored inner dialogue generates
bad judgment untutored inner dial
that's not coming from socrates i'm
tutored inner dialogue is driving
bad judgment
and it's hard to deal with again
precisely because
cognition is inherently dialogical and
that
is adaptive and because we have
incul enculturated narrative into us
because that's so adaptive
the ways in which that goes wrong are so
addictive and compelling and hard to
deal with
we get bad judgment now we need to
understand the way the stoics are using
this term
judgment
in order to do that we have to look at
the group of people that first
came out of antisthenes
so the line goes from socrates to and
tiff's the knees and then
he right so antisthenes is
uh the person i've been talking about
with
the learning to converse with yourself
and then he
has students that and one of the most
famous
of his students is
diogenes and diogenes is a cynic
now we we use this word incorrectly
in a degenerative fashion we think
somebody who's cynical because they
they don't believe in anything there's a
secret agenda that's not
what the ancient meaning of cynicism was
at all
it shows you how our culture really
deeply
misunderstands its own wisdom tradition
they are the way in which it has
malformed and
misunderstood many of these central
terms and ideas
okay so diogenes he's famous you
probably know i mean
he was on that one of the covers of the
led zeppelin album
he's figuring the tarot you know the
hermit carrying the lamp
right carrying the lamp looking for the
one uh honest person we'll come back to
that
in a minute but what the cynics like
diogenes
following entities slot the bad judgment
what's that what does they what do they
mean by bad judgment
well when we hear judgment we hear
belief what you believe but again
we have lost a lot of this uh let's this
comes from a german word right
believe in which translates
as beloved it's what you set your heart
on that's what judgment is
it's not generate it's not primarily
generating belief
how do we now understand it sentences or
propositions that we assert
this is the act of setting your heart on
something
setting your heart on something and
the idea here is that this is very much
like
uh dweck's work which we'll talk about
later
on uh mindsets the way we set our mind
and set our heart
which is not the same thing as just
having a set of beliefs
so think about when you what we mean
when we say you set your heart on
something it's beloved by us
um so we're finding it particularly
relevant and salient and important
we're binding our identity to it when
when someone is your beloved you you
don't just have beliefs about them
oh yes i believe they're a good person i
believe
believe that of course you have beliefs
about them that's i'm not denying that
but you don't
just have beliefs about them there is a
commitment
of what you find relevant salient
important identification
and you begin to internalize that person
and allow them to shape your identity in
a profound
way okay that's what we're talking about
with judgment here
we're not talking about simply the act
of coming to certain beliefs
we're talking about something much
deeper and more profound
and the cynics argued
that what's what our bad judgment is
is we set our heart on the wrong thing
that's what cynicism originally meant
so what the cynics thought is that most
people set their hearts
on things that are created by social
convention
rather than on natural or moral law and
then the idea here is
because social conventions change and
shift around
and are not ultimately grounded in
anything
deeply rational we will ultimately be
disappointed
when we set our heart on things that are
created by social convention
so diogenes what's he doing with that
lamp
well he's in the marketplace right and
he's doing this provocative thing
it's very interesting uh about um uh
the the kind of thing that's uh diabetes
doing he's not really offering
argument like socrates is and that shows
us another side of socrates that we tend
to forget
he's instead really trying to do this
provocative he's almost doing
performance art and he's
trying to provoke people he's carrying
this lamp around looking for
what and people are what are you looking
forward to these and you won't tell them
well what are you looking for
and they're in their mom they're in the
marketplace and they're doing all this
stuff what are you looking for what are
you looking for come on
and then he says i'm looking for one
honest person
so people are in the marketplace and
they're seeking and seeking and looking
and they're looking for all this stuff
right but
most of it is you know think about
saying think about this
entity that we all set our hearts on
money only exists by social convention
if you take out a coin
look at it remember this if we all agree
or
remember that it doesn't have any actual
inherent value
and that's what sometimes happens right
people panic and realize oh
this stuff doesn't really exist and then
it all collapses and falls apart
right so people are in the marketplace
doing all this
and but what they're not concerned with
is something
that has intrinsic value honesty
honesty and this comes from something in
fact socrates is famous for doing
he walked into the marketplace and he
said oh wow
look at all the things i don't need
so what the cynics engaged in
is two things together uh social
renunciation
and social provocation and what they're
trying to do with that
with that with that so the renunciation
the provocation are trying to bring
about two things
right so you sort of trying to start
working together to bring about
something
so you have the social renunciation
and that's renunce oh enunciation i
believe that's correct
and then social provocation like what i
just described with diogenes
that sort of performance art both of
these are working together
to create an existential reframing
people fundamentally reframing their
sense
of the agent arena relationship their
identity their existential mode
we talked a lot about that when we
talked about meta
and reciprocal opening so
diagrams for example left athens and
lived
outside of the city in a barrel famously
um this is where this comes from cynic
means living like a dog
right that's what it actually means so
he
so the cynics did not want to
set their hearts on all these things
that are created by social convention
kind of like sort of hippies right and
so they they
they they lived outside the city um and
then they would
and then they also did provocative
things because they were trying to get
people to really
existentially reframe and alter what
they find
relevant salient and important what they
identify with
fundamentally alter at an existential
level
what they set their hearts on famously
when diogenes was in
is barrel alexander alexander the great
here's the emperor of the world
he comes up to diogenes and he comes up
and he's got i always picture there's
all these
you know maybe even elements i don't
know why there's this big thing and they
come up and there's
diogenes and alexander says i am
alexander and alexander was very much
about creating this whole mythos
of him being a god man and he says to
diogenes i can give you anything you
want
anything what do you want and digest he
said can you move to a little
can you move a little to the left you're
blocking my sunlight
right social pronunciation social
provocation trying to
really refrain uh people
now what's interesting about this right
is the stoics
noted that there's a bit of a
contradiction well this is very powerful
stuff it's famous pictures of diogenes
in the barrel
and like i said carrying the lamp have
become you know regular
icons in our culture of people often
don't even know why
the fact that it was on the left
zeppelin album and in the tarot i think
is
is something very very important
okay so what did the stoics so there was
a guy named zeno and he was influenced
by
the cynics but he also loved plato and
he thought
we needed to put together the two sides
the
aspect of socrates that had come from
entities and the aspect of socrates that
had come from plato
and he picked up on a a a problem within
cynicism and this is the idea that the
cynics paid
too much attention to the objects
of bad judgment and not enough attention
to the process of judgment
too much emphasis and we do this this is
one of our besetting
cognitive biases we pay too much
attention to the
objects of our thought and the products
of our thought and very little attention
to the processes of our thinking of our
judgment
so the stoics said
we will talk about this but we want to
put
much more emphasis on this
the process because it's not what you're
setting your heart on
because they realize that this
that judgment can be on about anything
or practically anything
it's more the process of how you
set your heart upon things
all right so what's the process
of that they're interested in well it's
a process you're familiar with
it's a process that we have talked about
before
it is the process of and we
i used if you remember at the time when
we were doing the meditation course i
referenced the stoics it's the process
of co-identification
that i identification i'm always
doing this in a interdependent conjoined
fashion
i am assuming an identity as an agent
and i'm assigning identity to identities
to things
as an arena so right now i'm the teacher
you're the student
etc this is a classroom i'm assuming and
assigning identities and i'm doing that
mo i'm doing it largely unconsciously
automatically and reactively and
remember i gave you this little acronym
i'm doing it mindlessly
i'm doing it automatically and i'm doing
reactively and that is what is marring
my judgment
that is what is marring my judgment
and so this is all about the existential
modes
so the stoics and it we talked about
this when we're talking about meta
actually noted that there are two kinds
of modes remember that eric from got
this from the stoix
there is the having mode
and the being mode they are both
adaptive
do you remember so this is about needs
that are met by having
consuming and controlling and i treat
things categorically so they
can efficiently and effectively uh
consume them and control them and i
right so this marker is like the
previous marker and so i can exchange
that marker that's running out of ink
with this one and i could because it's a
marker i can quickly control it and use
it for what i need to do
that's great so this is you know
primarily about control
but there are needs that are met not by
controlling or consuming their needs are
met by
by transformation and development so
these are developmental needs these are
needs like becoming honest being an
honest person
being an honest person and these are
these don't sort of
uh they're not self-terminating the way
we
like when i drink enough water i drink
enough water but i never get to the
place where i say i'm honest enough
i don't need to be you know i don't need
to work on being honest
right that's a very dangerous place to
get to when you start to talk that way
all right so what the the stoics did is
right
and from this what from god and we
talked about this so how you know
meta contemplation is about learning to
discern
and distinguish between these two and
remember
the being mode remember stephen bachelor
argued that buddhism is all about
remembering the being mode satin
is that deep remembering of the being
mode
all right so
the stoics take it deeper than i
presented it because i was just
presenting
how it would help understanding meta and
buddhism at the time but the stoics
really go in here
and they say no no we're going to deepen
this ability to disturb
and distinguish between these we're
going to really help you get better at
dealing with modal confusion
all right so what do they do well
here's the and curiodon
the manual for living by epictetus one
of the great
philosophers and this is this is how it
begins this is his manual
for how to live well
and this is how this is its very
beginning
so i'm just trying to get the very first
page happiness and freedom
notice those two together by the way we
always think of stoicism as sort of this
dollar no
happiness and freedom begin with a clear
understanding of
one principle some things are within our
control
and some things are not it is only after
you have faced up to this
fundamental rule and learned to
distinguish between
what you can and can't control that
inner tranquility
and outer effectiveness inner
tranquility
anoraxia the epicureans outer
effectiveness
outer effectiveness is also important
remember that please
become possible
so
what the story say is one way in which
we
get into deep modal confusion is we
are deeply deluded about what's in our
control
and how much control we have so the
story to point out to two really
important
facts which one is the proliferation of
consequences
and the other is the fatality of all
things
okay so here is a fact we all know to be
true
and yet we ignore it almost moment by
moment
most of our plans fail and most of the
time we are disappointed with the
results of things
not always but most of the time we are
disappointed
frustrated and we fail in the sense that
things don't go as planned
why well this has to do with the fact
that
we like we're gonna do action a
and we intend for it to have consequence
b
great the problem is and think about
this when you take
medication there are always
side effects there are always side
effects and in fact
the side effects outnumber the intended
effects this is one of the problems
we're facing when we're trying to make
artificial intelligence
we just do an an action and we know what
the intended effect is
but right there's all these side effects
and we some we
pay attention to some of them and ignore
most of them
and that's key to our intelligence and
then here's the problem when
b occurs b not only produces what we
might foresee
c it produces this and each one of these
is right and you see what's happening
you get the proliferation of side
effects
and so for the stoics trying to control
it doesn't mean you don't act but
thinking that you can
move the world that's how they often put
it is
mostly delusional again they don't
they're not quietest
member outer effectiveness you're trying
so what you need to do
is you need to enhance your ability to
zero in on
the relevant side effects not just the
narrative
intention not just where the stories not
whether you're interest
you've got this in oh story this is how
it's going to go
that's okay that's this this but you
need to open up your ability to zero in
on much more of the world and
acknowledge how much of this
you do not have control over
so let's take something that i work with
daily
oh surely i have control over my my own
body
the stoics are saying no you don't and i
have meniere's disease right now
it's challenging me right now i'm
feeling a little bit of vertigo right
right and i have that i can do things i
can do
things that make a difference i'm
effective
but i can't control all of
it it's beyond me even aspects of my
body
now this is not to put you into despair
okay so hang on for hang on to this
what's the fatality of all things the
fatality of all things is
the universe is so complex remember what
it talked about about narrative bias
the universe is way beyond our narrative
bias
so there we have our stories
and we think these are this is the way
things are running
and romantic comedies really seduce us
into this and somehow
the universe and our stories yep the
practice
the fatality of death is death is fatal
it is fate it is an
aspect of fate remember we talked about
this meaning that death comes
independent of how great your narrative
is you can have met
this wonderful woman who you adore and
is amazing
and is lifting your heart as no other
person has
and you step into traffic and you hit my
truck
the truck doesn't go oh well john has
finally found
the love of his life choc ichi
it's fatal it's absurd and camus made a
big deal of this right
so when we the the stoics and this is
kind of harsh this is where you get the
idea of the stiff upper lip of stoicism
the stomachs want to hold up in our face
this is diogenes holding up the lamp
pay attention to the way things really
are pay attention to the way things
really are
so what is in our control
our judgment so the thing we take when
we focus on the object
and we're going to try and control the
object
we're actually probably going to lose to
a large degree for all the reasons i've
just said
and what what we don't pay attention to
what we're transparent what we're
looking
through is our judgment but we can
exercise tremendous control over over a
judgment
if we properly train it if we properly
train it
so again what's our judgment mean
setting our heart on something
what we find relevant what we find
salient how we identify
how we create identities agent arena
relationships existential modes
and the the the stoics have this term
pros
which means paying attention to how you
pay attention it's one of their
fundamental principles
paying attention to how you pay
attention which is why a lot of people
compare stoicism
to mindfulness and buddhism
okay so what you want to do is get to a
place
where you are
right realizing that meaning making
in the sense of what you find relevant
and salient and identified with is
much more in your control and
what that means is also meaning making
is
proper to the being mode that's what the
meat being mode is all about
is a way of getting you to right
shift into the being mode
and the idea here is we can do this
better remember we talked about this
reciprocal opening
the stoics have a very similar thing
they talk about joy
which is learning to flow with nature
but you didn't think about that in
connection with stoicism
joy and learning to flow with nature
so what we have to do in order to
properly tutor
our what follows from this and what we
have to do to properly tutor our
judgment
is we have to make we have to learn in
our attention
to make a distinction between events
and our judgments about the events
because they are almost always and this
is what narrative does
they're almost always confused together
they're confused together so we have to
get better
at tracking
how things are actually unfolding we
have to get better
at tracking reality
as much as possible we want what we find
relevant
to as much as possible track what is
real
and remember that doesn't necessarily
mean what comes most readily or easily
to us so this
is the stoic practice of rationality
rationality here doesn't mean
inference control primarily like or or
just being logical
the stoics actually put three things
together logic
ethics and physics
and logic is much more like psychologic
it's much more
learning an ecology of practices
for enhancing and improving your
capacity for judgment your ability to
make relevance track what is most real
and that's a very hard thing to do
okay so
a better way to think about this is more
like the logos
getting finding make those patterns of
intelligibility
that are relevant to us but also track
the real patterns in the world
and leave and here's the thing logos
your ability to discern
and be aware of the logos is ultimately
dependent
on your inner dia logos your inner
dialogue your inner dialogue
so
how do we transform our inner dialogue
i'll just briefly indicate what we're
going to talk about next time and
and then give you some ideas about some
practices we're going to engage in
so the basic idea and one way you can
understand
all of stoicism is stoicism is the
practice of internalizing socrates this
goes right back to entities
we talked about internalizing the sage
how do we internalize socrates
so that we can transform our inner deal
logos
so that we can become more rational so
that our ability to set our hearts more
reliably tracks
the real patterns and so that we are
we are more reliably within the being
mode
and that we are more reliably free from
frustration despair and disappointment
and free to experience and drink from
the depths of the being mode itself
that's what we're going to talk about
next time
we're going to talk about what socratic
self-knowledge looks like
and we're going to notice the
connections we can reach back to
philosophical contemplated
companionships
and reach forward we'll look forward
foreshadowing
platonic uh dialectic and we're going to
start talking about practices for how we
do this
how do we cultivate uh rationality well
active open-mindedness
but we're also going to teach you how to
do that uh how
and this internalization it's going to
involve perspectival transformation
i'm going to teach you about the view
from above objective
seeing the pre-meditation we're going to
take a look
at some of the stoic spiritual exercises
from buzari
so that's what's coming it's so exciting
and it's so enriching
i i think i trespassed a little bit on
our time for questions today
i'll make sure next time to uh to uh
end a little bit earlier but i needed i
wanted to get to at least this point so
i hope you forgive me
uh for trespassing a little bit into the
question time we'll make sure that we uh
we i
i set aside 15 minutes next saturday uh
to address the questions that are
probably
probably mounting um so we're just going
to end it here for today
and i i i hope you can see i'm very
excited about this
stoicism has a lot to offer us i i have
a lot of books
i would recommend getting the interior
don by epictetus
i get the meditations by marcus aurelius
um this is a particularly good
translation by mark forstatter
the spiritual teachings of marcus
aurelius
and and then i'll recommend a whole
bunch of books to you
also next time it's so great to be doing
this with you all and i love being in
the saturday sanga
and so keep reading the mclennan i know
i haven't given you anything to practice
yet we need to get the background
next time we'll finish off the
background and we'll start right into
the exercises and the spiritual
exercises
so i look forward to seeing you all then
take good care everybody
okay